<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the publick commencement at Cambridge, Sunday in the afternoon, July iij, 1698 by Francis Hutchinson ...</title>
            <author>Hutchinson, Francis, 1661-1739.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45245</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3831</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7531</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13513520</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13513520</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99864</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45245)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99864)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 791:41)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the publick commencement at Cambridge, Sunday in the afternoon, July iij, 1698 by Francis Hutchinson ...</title>
                  <author>Hutchinson, Francis, 1661-1739.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Edmund Jeffery ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Cambridge :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms IX, 10 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99864:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED at the Publick Commencement AT <hi>CAMBRIDGE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>SUNDAY in the Afternoon <hi>July</hi> iij. 1698.</p>
            <p>By <hi>FRANCIS HUTCHINSON,</hi> D. D. Preacher at St. <hi>James</hi>'s in <hi>Bury</hi> St. <hi>Edmunds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>CAMBRIDGE,</hi> Printed for <hi>Edmund Jeffery,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> 1698.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:99864:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99864:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PSALM ix. former part of the x. v.</hi> And they that know thy Name will put their Truſt in thee.</head>
            <p>BY thoſe who know God's Name, are meant thoſe who know God himſelf and his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Thoſe who by Studying his Word, and his Works, and the Footſteps of his Power, and Wiſdom, and Love to his Creatures, have poſſeſt their Minds with Right and Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Thoughts of God, and are ſenſible how Great and Glorious a being he is, ſuch Perſons as thoſe will not be afraid to put their Truſt in him: though the things they have heard of him in times paſt, are wonderful: And though they are as great which they expect from him in times to come, they will conſider who it is that is to perform them, and what marvelous works he hath done before, and then Faith will be an eaſy Virtue to them, for they will never fear, but that he who can fetch Water out of a ſtony Rock, will be able to give Bread alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:99864:3"/>This ſeems the natural meaning of the words, That <hi>thoſe who know God, will Truſt him:</hi> but this is general, and may be apply'd different waies.</p>
            <p>It may be underſtood of thoſe publick Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances which Religious Governments may expect in their difficulties, and dangers.</p>
            <p>Or, it may be uſed for the ſupport of virtuous men, with reſpect to the courſe of their own lives, and affairs in particular.</p>
            <p>Or laſtly, It may be applyed to God's Decrees, and Dealings, and Government of our Human Race in general, and may ſerve to ſtrengthen our Belief, and expectation of thoſe happy things which make up our common Faith.</p>
            <p>And it is this laſt which I intend (by the aſſiſtance of God) to diſcourſe upon.</p>
            <p>For when we view in our minds the courſe of our Race, from its firſt riſe, and beginning upon Earth, through the ſtrange States it hath gone tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough, and caſt in our minds what ſeems moſt like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be the concluſion and end of ſuch a ſort of Race, after ſuch a kind of life: and when we ſpeak that Common Faith, and Belief in this matter, which we have not deviſed our ſelves, but received from our Fathers, and which ſeems to us to be grounded upon very good Reaſon: That this Scene is to paſs off, and a juſt Judgment, and Review of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:99864:3"/>
all that hath paſt in it, and a Heaven, and a Hell are to follow in its place; the minds of many, that are Ingenious enough otherwiſe, are overſet with the ſtrangeneſs, and greatneſs of the things, ſo that inſtead of believing of them heartily, they think Religious Men are Credulous, and vain in raiſing their thoughts to ſuch high expectations.</p>
            <p>It happens to Prophets, and Religious Men, and Preachers of theſe things, from theſe unbelievers, as it happens to Philoſophers, and Learned Men, from the ignorant multitude. For let the Graveſt and Wiſeſt Men ſpeak before Common People, what Demonſtrations they have made concerning the Syſtem of the World, and the magnitudes and diſtances of the Stars, and the other reaſonable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable ſuſpicions of things; becauſe the Accounts are above the Report that ſence makes, they think much Learning hath made them mad, and do more than ſmile to think how Credulous Schollars are.</p>
            <p>And this is almoſt more than a Compariſon, it is ſo very near akin to the real Nature of the caſe before us: for as Coſmography is the Philoſophy of the World; Divinity is the Philoſophy of God, and its Inhabitants. One laies before us, the Nature, and Condition of the Earth; the other laies before us, the Fate and Fortune of that Race which God hath put into it. The ſame thing that overſets men's minds in the Belief of one, overſets them in the other, and that is, the greatneſs and ſtrangeneſs of them: For it is with difficulty, &amp; ſlowly that we
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99864:4"/>
raiſe our minds to the Majeſty of God in either. And Men muſt be let into the Belief of one, by the ſame way that they are let into the Belief of the other. To convince a Man of the Greatneſs and Majeſty of Nature, and the World, there is no way but to Demonſtrate its Greatneſs in ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar parts, and by that he will gueſs of himſelf that the reſt muſt be proportionable. And to give Men Reaſon for expecting great Revolutions in God's Government, and great Rewards and Puniſhments in times to come; there ſeems no way ſo likely, as to lay before them, things as ſtrange and aſtoniſhing which God hath done in times paſt, and moſt of which are now before our Faces: And if we can do that, they will Believe without difficulty, becauſe they will ſee that ſuch wondrous matters are common things with him. They will ſee them proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and even with thoſe that are paſt, ſo that inſtead of thinking it ſtrange God's diſpenſations to come ſhould be great, they will think it ſtrange if they ſhould not, for why ſhould not God's works be all of a piece, and anſwerable to one another.</p>
            <p>This is what I aim at in this Diſcourſe, and I think it will not be improper from theſe Words. For truſting in God, does very naturally take in, all the expectations we have of what he hath Promiſed; and knowing God's Name, is a raiſing our minds to a juſt Sence of his Nature by the Contemplation of his works of Creation, and Providence: and having thus opened my way to my deſign, I ſhall apply it particularly to theſe three points: The Immortality
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:99864:4"/>
of Man, and the Rewards, and Puniſhments of the other Life, that is Heaven and Hell.</p>
            <p>Only this I muſt premiſe, that I propoſe not in this Diſcourſe to make the direct and proper proof we have of theſe points, for that reſts upon the plain promiſe of God, and the Reſurrection of our Saviour: But ſince there are a ſort of Men, who, rather than Believe that God ever made ſuch Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, will deny the Faith of Hiſtory, break through all the Arguments which they allow themſelves in other caſes, and call all Men Lyars, as if the Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt and Sobereſt part of our Race was ſo very vain, and falſe, that we could depend upon nothing that came through their hands: and ſince they do this, chiefly, becauſe the things revealed ſeem ſtranger and greater than they know how to Believe of God Almighty; therefore I propoſe theſe Conſiderations of God, and his works, as a proper Anſwer and Remedy for their perverſeneſs.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Firſt Point then that I ſhall Diſcourſe on is the Immortality of Man. That our weak Race which is made up of periſhing materials, that are almoſt dead while they are alive, and are haſting to a change that hath all the appearance of ending, ſhould not dye really for all that when they ſeem to do ſo, but live on, and have their ſhare in all the Revolutions which the World is to undergo, as long as God himſelf ſhall have his being:</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:99864:5"/>This is a great thing no doubt of it, and ſhocks Mens minds; but let us conſider what we have in the Knowledge of God, and his Works which may further us in the Belief of it.</p>
            <p>And Firſt, We are to Conſider, that tho' it be a wonderful thing that frail Man ſhould continue for ever, yet the eternal duration it ſelf muſt really be. Whether we ſhall be alive in it, or be dead things, That muſt run its endleſs courſe.</p>
            <p>And as there muſt, of neceſſity, be an eternity of time, and duration; ſo through it all, God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty muſt, as neceſſarily, have his being, and be perfect as he is now, in Wiſdom, Power, and Goodneſs.</p>
            <p>And tho' we may not ſay it is neceſſary, yet I dare ſay, any Man will grant it a thouſand times more likely, that thorough all that Eternity, God will preſerve a World, and Creatures in being, that, as there are now, ſo there may alwaies be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, Creatures who ſhall feel themſelves hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py out of his ſtores, and Praiſe his bounty.</p>
            <p>We may not ſay God will have it ſo, becauſe it will be any acceſſion to his own Happineſs, and yet, to a beneficent, good being, the communicat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Happineſs to Creatures who ſhould be able to know the giver, looks ſo very like to a true plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and ſatisfaction, that it is one of the things men wonder at, why God began ſo late as ſix thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:99864:5"/>
Years ſince to Create; and ſome, rather than ſuppoſe that God would ever be without a World, and ſuch ſenſible Creatures before him, they ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to ſay, That there muſt have been other Worlds before this of ours. Now not to ſpeak of this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is one of thoſe many Points we are not able to Fathom, we Learn ſo much from it certainly, that the common Sence of Mankind is ſo far from thinking it unlikely that God ſhould have a World, and Creatures before him alwaies in being, that they are for believing elder, and more, in the times that are paſt.</p>
            <p>But this is only by the way. We ſee that ſince Eternity muſt be: and ſince God Almighty muſt of neceſſity be through it all, it is eaſy to grant that God will alſo have Creatures alwaies before him. The Point then comes to this: Whether is moſt likely, that God ſhould chuſe to continue Creatures before him, by giving Eternity to the Souls of Men: or by letting them dye, and end as they do in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, and by raiſing up other new ones in their places.</p>
            <p>And for this point— If the Souls of Men are really Aboliſhed, and end at Death, I do not know but we may ſay, that they are the only Subſtances in the whole compaſs of beings that are ſo.</p>
            <p>The Reaſon why I ſpeak thus is that Principle in Philoſophy, which I ſuppoſe is uncontroverted, that the Deſtruction of all Material Beings is not a real
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:99864:6"/>
end, or abolition of their Subſtance, and Being, but a change into ſomething elſe, and through all their Tranſmutations, there is not a Particle of their real Subſtance loſt. But if the Souls of Men do not live in their proper Perſons, they are aboliſhed, and are extinct: For no body ever Dreamt of their being Changed into any other Forms that ſhould preſerve their Subſtance.</p>
            <p>I do not lay much weight upon this, but it does not ſeem probable, that the moſt Excellent Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance that God hath made, ſhould be leſs fixt in Nature, and Being, than the meaneſt and moſt contemtible: and if it be not, then it follows ſtrongly, that the Soul does not end at Death, but only ſuffers a natural periodical change, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues in ſuch a State, and way as God hath prepared for it.</p>
            <p>But let this be as it will: I build not upon it. The Point I ſhall argue from is what the Text offers us, the Mind of God towards his Creatures, that is, which ſeems moſt likely, that God ſhould preſerve Creatures before him by continuing theſe, or that he ſhould ſuffer theſe to fall back out of being, and raiſe up new ones in their ſtead for ever.</p>
            <p>And if the Queſtion was put concerning meer A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimals, whoſe diſſolution is made without any grief, or ſorrow, or reflections of their own Minds about it; we ſhould not need to look far for an Anſwer. Or if it was put concerning an inanimate God, <hi>i. e.</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:99864:6"/>
concerning dead nature, and a chain of cauſes that were ſuppoſed to have circulated Mankind into Life, the cauſes themſelves not knowing how, A ſhort Anſwer would have ſerv'd that alſo; For, no doubt, but as Nature, and Cauſes had put Man together without knowing what they did, they would have let us fall again into pieces, as ſoon as our ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients moved that way.</p>
            <p>But the queſtion is put concerning a very living God, and Beings that God hath raiſed to a high degree of Life, and Communication with himſelf. For we were made by that Wiſe Creator whom we dayly Worſhip. He hath lay'd in our Natures the Grounds of ſuch Underſtanding and Knowledge of himſelf, and works, as inables us for a Divine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercourſe, and Love, and all the happy Paſſions which follow from an humble Worſhip, and reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſervice of himſelf. He hath given us to taſte a Thouſand Pleaſures with Judgment, and Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: and added clear Notions of a higher happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and of the vaſt difference of enjoying of it, for the ſhort Term of threeſcore Years and ten, and of enjoying of it alwaies. And after this I need not add it as another Gift, for there muſt, of neceſſity, follow from theſe, ſtrong deſires to continue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies, if it may be, in Life and Happineſs: For no Creature can be ſo temperately indifferent to its own Happineſs, as to ſee Life, and God, and his Works, and not deſire, if it be poſſible, to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in Life amongſt them, and be Happy with them. And therefore the whole Reaſonable Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99864:7"/>
groans and travels with deſires of Life. Even Nature, in all of us, makes vehement Prayers, and many have added excellent Virtues and Service, and Obedience, and even voluntary Deaths and Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms for God's Honour, in hopes to move God by them that they might not dye indeed. And ſince God will have Creatures ever before him, is it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to be thought that theſe ſhould be they? I wo' not ſay, on the other ſide, that, in a Moral Sence, it is neceſſary they ſhould: but I will ſay, that, one ſingle Miracle, and Promiſe of God ſhould be ſufficient to Satisfy all Mankind that they will. For, after God hath raiſed Creatures to ſuch an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercourſe with himſelf, and Sence of things, and and vehement neceſſary deſires of living, a turning of them out of Being when he can continue them with a word, looks like a ſevere Act. If indeed God had not Created us, not being had been no affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: but to bring ſuch an excellent Creature ſo near to Happineſs, that he might tear away his longing Eyes from enjoying it: To bring him into Being, that he might have a ſorrowful <hi>exit:</hi> We muſt ſpeak indeed with humility as becomes us: but the thing would put a ſtrong Expoſtulation, and Plea, into the Creatures Mouth. I need not ſpeak the Plea at large, for ſuch deſtruction of Virtuous Men is not the Mind of God, and they who know God rightly, would hardly ask for a Sign or Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle to convince them that it is not.</p>
            <p>But if the Eternal Duration be granted, there is</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:99864:7"/>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The greatneſs of the Glory and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſeems hard to be thought true. For our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion does ſpeak glorious, and happy things, both of the place of Heaven, and the Inhabitants that dwell in it: And it lets us know moreover, that even thoſe great deſcriptions, are but borrowed ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions from ſuch things as we underſtand, but that the Happineſs it ſelf is ſomething that is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, than we can yet conceive.</p>
            <p>And for the furthering of us in our Belief of this, I will only oppoſe, this preſent World, and work of God which we are ſure God hath made, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us for a dwelling-place.</p>
            <p>Let us caſt then our Thoughts, and Minds through the vaſt ſtretch of ſpace in which it ſtands. Conſider how it is fill'd with Sun, and Moon, and Thouſand Stars. Think of their Myſtick Dance, ſo juſt, ſo ſtrange. Their Motions ſwifter than Bullets fly, yet punctual to their time and place: Their magnitudes above what Thought can reach, yet ſteady, and even in their violent carreer: All things vaſt, every thing rapid, yet beautiful, and unconfuſed, and regular as an Army marches. Our Globe of Earth makes one amongſt them, and bears its part: this pondrous Maſs, half Land, half Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, with ſo many Lakes, Deſerts, Foreſts, burning Hills, Iſles, and habitable Lands, with our ſtrange Race that dwells upon it, We either ſwim or hang, together with our Earth, amongſt thoſe Stars, like an enchanted thing: And tho' we ſee, and feel our
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:99864:8"/>
Earth to be a dead lumpiſh heap of matter, yet it keeps its time and place, as ſteadily as if it was all Thought, and Eye. And of thoſe who cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve there ſhall be a Heaven, I would ask, Would they have believed there ſhould have been ſuch a World as this is if it had been told them? If theſe unbelieving Men had been Created before it, and it had been lay'd before them, by ſome Meſſenger from God, That God was about to Build ſuch a glorious piece of work for their Habitation, Would they not have believed it leſs, and thought it more unlikely, than the new Heavens and Earth which we expect now?</p>
            <p>And yet this Fabrick of the World is really a Thouſand times greater, and more wonderful in it ſelf, than it is in our Thoughts: For we only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Creation, as a Travaller ſhould admire ſome Illuſtrious Palace, through a Proſpective, from ſome diſtant Hill: And tho we are indeed dwellers in a little Angle of it, We do no more underſtand the Beauty, and Uſes, and Greatneſs, and Wiſdom of God's World, than ſuch a diſtant Obſerver could Judge of the Contrivance, and Convenience of ſuch a Houſe that he views ſo far off. And if, inſtead of being ſuch remote Spectators, we could ſee it at a nearer view: If, inſtead of being chained to our little ſpot, we could leave our Earth, and raiſe our ſelves till we were amongſt thoſe Celeſtial Bodies: And, with enlarged Minds, could comprehend that deep Contrivance by which our Earth and they, have made their myſterious courſe, by a perpetual
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:99864:8"/>
motion: And as God hath not made an Herb upon our Earth but for ſome good end, could we ſee the true, and proper end for which God Created thoſe, for he did not make ſuch mighty works, only to afford that little Light that guides our nights: And could we ſee thoſe great bodies, and their true uſes, as a Stranger views ſome Noble Houſe, from room to room, and ſide to ſide; there would be no more Spirit left in us. We ſhould Believe any thing that the Maker of ſuch a World hath Promiſed: And as for Seats of Bliſs for Virtuous Souls, and Glorious Manſions for thoſe whom this great Creator ſhould delight to Honour, inſtead of objecting the ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and difficulty of the thing, we ſhould be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up with humble wonder, how great, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious thoſe Manſions ſhould be. This ſhall ſuffice for the <hi>Second</hi> Point.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The <hi>Third</hi> is the Puniſhments of the other World.</p>
            <p>And under this Head I ſhall not offer at any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination, how much of the Deſcriptions we have of them is Literal, and how much Methapho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical, and Popular: let there be as much Metaphor as there will, yet ſince they will be what is ſuitable, and fit for falſe and impious Men: And ſince they be Eternal, for ſo, no doubt, the Souls of all Men are, both good and bad: And ſince, in the caſe of pain and miſery, the feeling does alwaies greatly exceed the imagination, I doubt not but the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern and apprehenſion we ſhould really have of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:99864:9"/>
them, ought, in reaſon, to be ten times greater, than what the generality of Men have, when they hear the moſt Tragical Repreſentations.</p>
            <p>But to the fears of this ſort, unbelieving Men oppoſe the great goodneſs of God. They think the <hi>Text</hi> I am ſpeaking of is on their ſide, and that they know not God who repreſent him ſo Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible.</p>
            <p>And I Confeſs the Superlative Deſcriptions of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite indulgence, and longing for our Happineſs, and a ſeverity in tormenting us, as infinitly inexora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, do ſeem to ſtand at a wide diſtance from one another: And I believe many expreſſions of this ſort have ſomething <hi>ad hominem.</hi> But whatever allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance may be made to ſuch waies of ſpeaking in other places, in this Auditory, even upon this Point, we muſt endeavour to ſpeak with juſt expreſſions.</p>
            <p>I make not this <hi>Preface</hi> as if I had any thing to follow it, that ſhould leſſen the Divine Goodneſs: that would be Blaſphemy in the higheſt. God's Goodneſs is Perfect, and ſo tempered with Wiſdom and Juſtice as makes a fairer, and more perfect Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of the Judge of all the Earth, than an infinite indulgence would do. And as his Goodneſs in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral is perfect, his <hi>Philanthropy,</hi> and Love of our Race is ſincere, and deſigns our Happineſs if we hinder it not our ſelves: He hath given us inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of that in abundance, and eſpecially in his ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to us our Saviour, and his Goſpel, for our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99864:9"/>
But then he hath let us know as effectually, that his Love of our Race is not ſo great, as his Love of True Excellency and Virtue, and hatred of baſe qualities. He hath given us abundant proof, that his indulgence of our Perſons is not ſo infinite but he can very eaſily make us miſerable and ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, if we make ourſelves deſerving to be ſo: And tho' great pains, and ſufferings be included in ſuch a ſtate; He hath given us very ſatisfactory proof, that it is not contrary to his goodneſs, but very well agreable with his Nature, to ſuffer baſe, and wicked Creatures to endure them.</p>
            <p>And that we might not flatter, and deceive our ſelves in a matter, where all we have lies at ſtake, if we look about into the works of God, he hath written this part of his Mind, in as clear Characters as he hath his Goodneſs.</p>
            <p>And let the Judgment of God upon the faln An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels be our firſt Example in this caſe. Amongſt us, it is no Diſpute, but that there are <hi>Myriads,</hi> infinite numbers of glorious Spirits baniſh'd by God, from the Regions of Bliſs. When by an unjuſt, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful Rebellion, they made themſelves unworthy of the Glory, and Happineſs he gave them, he would not diſhonour his Government by maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or ſuffering them to be happy in their diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, but condemned them to ſuch Conditions as they deſerved. Now by his puniſhing them, let us weigh our Arguments againſt his puniſhing our Race. Let us imagine we ſee ſo many glorious Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, falling under God's Juſtice, from the bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:99864:10"/>
of Heaven, to the miſeries they endure. Let us ſet before our Minds, the Torments they have gone thorough, in ſo many long Ages, as have paſt ſince that righteous Sentence: And then let us urge our Arguments for the impoſſibility of God's pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing wickedneſs. But there is no diſputing againſt matter of Fact, and whatever Arguments might be plauſibly urged before the experiment, as perhaps they were ſuch as deceived the new Created Angels, yet after the experiment, they ought not to deceive Children: For it is a plain Argument, what hath been, may be. And what God hath done once, He may do again, if the caſe be the ſame, becauſe he is the ſame, and being alwaies infinitly good, he muſt be alwaies infinitly, and equally an Enemy to unjuſt, and unreaſonable Creatures, and Actions.</p>
            <p>But becauſe Men who are willing to deceive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves will urge all the differences they can find out betwixt Angels and us, we will therefore conſider God's Providences, and Righteous Judgments upon us Men.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> Meditating upon theſe Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in the 46. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 8. <hi>v.</hi> calls upon Men to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the works of the Lord, what deſolations he hath made in the Earth.</p>
            <p>At firſt when he had Created the World good, and every way fitted for a happy Life, He Curſed it becauſe of ſin, and half ſpoiled ſuch a glorious piece of Workmanſhip, becauſe Man did not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:99864:10"/>
a happyer to live in. For let Men call theſe Pains and Sorrows, and Deaths that are upon us, Natural Calamities, that is only cheating our ſelves with a word, and with a very improper one for thoſe evils that are lay'd upon us by a living and thinking, and governing God. If they had hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened by a train of unthinking cauſes, and a fatal courſe of dead Nature, Natural Calamities had been their proper Name: but coming from a perfect Mind who does all things with Deſign, and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Juſtice, they are Puniſhments; and ſhow us very effectually, that it is not contrary to his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to puniſh wickedneſs, and diſobedience.</p>
            <p>For the wickedneſs again of Man, God brought a Flood of Waters upon the World, and except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Eight Perſons, drowned every Soul that breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the Earth. Millions that knew not their Right Hand from their Left, were drowned in their Mothers Arms, and Fathers and Children were ſwept away together. Men would not believe that: And though God ſent a Preacher to give them warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing while the Ark was preparing, yet ſtill it could not enter into their Minds, but that God would be more Merciful. But they argued ſo vainly, till the Flood was upon them.</p>
            <p>Now theſe Examples are as ſo many Monuments ſet up to Teach us, that we ought not to argue, that God's Goodneſs will not ſuffer him to puniſh, becauſe he hath ſhown us he will, and our Forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have found it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:99864:11"/>To come ſtill nearer, even to our own Age and Sight, and there will be no uncertainty. If we take but the preſent Face of things, and place before our Thoughts, the Sorrows, Pains, and Deaths, of our own, or of any Generation, we have Example ſufficient, as much as we need; for, abating for the different way, and the commonneſs which leſſens our Sence of it, allowing for that, we have the Fall and the Flood both, acted over again, in every Generation.</p>
            <p>For in what, I pray, does the multitude of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful Deaths that deſtroys every Age, fall ſhort of a Deluge? They differ indeed in the way, and time of deſtroying, but there is no difference in the deſolation, this one thing excepted, that whereas the Deluge left Eight Perſons, this takes the Eight alſo, and leaves not ſo much as one.</p>
            <p>And for the Pains, and Diſeaſes, and Sorrows, and Griefs, that alwaies lye upon Mankind, and are haſting ſome towards their end, and actually killing others, what can be a more ſad proſpect than this if we ſee it rightly? So many Afflictions and Croſſes, ſuch numbers of Deſolate Widows, and Fatherleſs Children, ſuch great poverty, and want as many feel. The ſinking Hearts of Slaves, and Captives, and Oppreſſed, and weary Servants. The terrors of thoſe places where they hide themſelves in the Dens, and Caves of the Earth, for fear of their Neighbours Swords. The languiſhing decays, or the torturing pains of Mens Bodies, while their
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:99864:11"/>
Eyes fail to ſee their certain Deaths a coming: Or the ſtill deeper Griefs of wounded Spirits, and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled Minds where the unſeen Arrows of God ſtick faſteſt and deepeſt of all others, and even drive on many to haſten their own Deaths, in hopes, that way, to lay down that Burden which is greater than they can bear. It is a Bleſſing to us that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monneſs of theſe things does, in ſome meaſure, har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den us from the true Thoughts that this caſe ſeems to require, for otherwiſe the multitude of Sorrows that are in the World, and their nearneſs to our ſelves, would draw too dark a Cloud over our lives. But as this mighty Army of Afflicted, Suffering, Dying Men, are alwaies under God's Eye, and Hand, let us place them, at this time, before our Minds: And if we add to the Thought, how many of theſe are Righteous, Pious Perſons, who have endeavoured in the courſe of their Lives, both to bear, and to do the will of God, we ſhall hardly forbear applying our Saviour's Speech, <hi>If theſe things be done in the green Tree, what ſhall be done in the dry?</hi> If God laies ſuch Judgments upon mixt multitudes, what Puniſhments will he make uſe of when he ſhall have ſeparated the Goats from the Sheep, and ſet the Wicked by themſelves? If ſuch Afflictions, and Sorrows as theſe, are for Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, for Government, and good uſes, under the time of tryal, what greater Miſeries muſt there be in ſtore againſt that time, when the Judge of all the Earth ſhall diſtribute Juſtice amongſt all his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects? His Puniſhments indeed will not be greater than Mens evil works deſerve, for he will do wrong
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:99864:12"/>
to none; but what their ſins do deſerve, he hath given us ſufficient Aſſurance, that it is not againſt his Nature to inflict them.</p>
            <p>And thus I have Diſcourſed thoſe <hi>Three Points</hi> I propoſed; I am ſenſible how far below the Dignity of ſo great a Subject: for which way can we raiſe our Thoughts to the Majeſty of God's Works. But ſince the Revelation, and Promiſe of theſe things is clear (as it is moſt certainly, unleſs our Race be ſo degenerate a brood that we can be ſure of nothing that comes to us through one anothers Hands) I perſwade my ſelf that even this Diſcourſe, ſuch as it is, muſt make it very reaſonable for us to expect them.</p>
            <p>For, to urge thoſe ſeveral Arguments now to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the Concluſion. We who are the preſent living Generation, we ſtand upon our preſent time, as upon a Mountain betwixt two Gulfs, betwixt two Eternities, one paſt and gone, the other as long in coming. God Almighty ſhall have his Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thorough both: And wherefore may not God ſhow forth his Power in as wondrous works in one, as he hath done in the other? Let unbelieving Men ſit down, and think, and anſwer that, what Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances they have that God will not be as marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in his Dealings with his Creatures in times to come, as he hath been in times paſt: And ſince in the paſt Eternity, there hath been a Creation, a Fall, a Flood, the coming of the Son of God, and his Aſcenſion into Heaven: Why, in the Eternity
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:99864:12"/>
to come, may there not be a Conflagration, a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, a Day of Judgment, and a Heaven and Hell? They will ſay, I know, that the things are ſtrange, and great, and wonderful. But then I An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, We live in a World of Wonders. It is a Wonder that there ſhould be ſuch a World as this is, which God hath given us for a Dwelling-place. It is a Wonder there ſhould be in it ſuch a ſort of Creatures as we are, and in ſuch a manner of life as we live. And indeed, tho' I have hitherto only ſpoken of the paſt, and preſent works of God as great to ſuch a degree as to make it eaſy to believe that God may do others though greater, yet I am verily perſwaded, That if we could raiſe our Minds to a true View, and Thought of things, we ſhould Confeſs, that, for real Wonder, and ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, this preſent World exceeds, and goes beyond the other.</p>
            <p>The Reaſon why I ſpeak thus is this: That mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which are full of Glory, and Goodneſs, and Happineſs, and Juſtice, and Majeſty, ſuch as we expect in Heaven, they are ſuch as we naturally look for from a being of infinite Wiſdom, Power, and Goodneſs who can Create perfect, and happy Creatures with as much caſe as imperfect; And thoſe things, to conſidering Men, ſeem ſtrangeſt, where there are mixtures of evil, that ſeem to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue weakneſs, and diſapointment, and the diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, and ſeem as if not good, ſuch as this World abounds with: They are ſuch as puz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zle Wiſe Men moſt, why, and wherefore God
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:99864:13"/>
ſhould ſuffer them, when he can prevent them with ſuch eaſe.</p>
            <p>And, for Concluſion, let us try, in our Thoughts, to View, as in a Map, or Landskip, all the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Works of God, from firſt to laſt, the riſing World, its time of Tryal, and then a glorious Scene of Saints, with God, in Joy, for ever; and of all theſe, the laſt, the Heaven is eaſieſt to our Thoughts.</p>
            <p>The new made World, at firſt call'd out of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and with a word commanded out of nothing, that is what no Heart could ever have Thought. But when that was paſt and over, of our ſelves then we ſhould frame a Scene of happy things, Creatures praiſing, loving God, and Bleſt, and Happy in his Love, ſuch as we expect in Heaven: In our own Thoughts we ſhould run to that, and not eaſily be brought back to ſee a ſtranger face of things before it. To ſee the Creatures God had made, Blaſpheming, Curſing him that brought them into being: To ſee a Scene of Rapine, Blood, and Falſhood: Wickedneſs in Proſperity: Virtue under Foot: Rebellion againſt God, under his own Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and yet in Triumph: and Duty to him and Obedience, before his Face, yet low, and trod on: And this, not for a ſhort ſpace as one would think, but long, and mournful Ages, till the Hearts of Righteous Men do almoſt fail, down to our own unhappy Age, in which we ſee the graceleſs Actours: It is this, this is the wondrous part of all God's
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:99864:13"/>
Works, and the ſtrangeſt Scene, ſo ſtrange, and poſing that nothing can unriddle it but a Heaven, and Hell to come.</p>
            <p>And therefore, for Concluſion of all. It is ſo far from being unlikely that there ſhould be a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and a Hell, that one can hardly forbear ſaying that there muſt be ſuch, if the Scene of the World be lay'd with Wiſdom, and proportion: and the concluſion of its courſe be anſwerable, and of a piece with its beginning: But I will ſpeak with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, and with all the humility that may be, we may ſafely ſay, That ſince God hath Reveal'd it to us, that in the order of his Government there is one great Revolution to come, which will bring in with it a Heaven and a Hell, we are ſure, we know they will certainly be: and thoſe who are afraid they ſhould not, and find it hard to Truſt him, they do not know him, nor have any right or wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Notions of him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now to this King Immortal, from whom we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect theſe things, together with his Son, and Bleſſed Spirit, be aſcribed of us, and of all Creatures, in Heaven and Earth, All poſſible Praiſe, Honour, and Thanksgiving, now and evermore.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
